My name is James Smith.
I used to work in a budget gym in
Bracknell on the gym
floor, earning £30 an hour.
And over the last seven to eight years,
I migrated into an online platform where
I've had over 100,000 online clients,
and I now still operate an eight-figure
personal training business.
Is that possible for you? I'm not sure.
Maybe, maybe not.
But what is possible
is at least hitting your first 100K a
year.
So I'm going to give you a step-by-step
guide of the eight things
that you need for
that to happen. And no,
you don't need to be funny or hilarious.
No, you don't need a massive following.
No, you don't need to be chiseled
and have a six-pack all year round.
You just need to do these things.
Number one,
you are going to need to do some
personal training on the gym floor.
I think that 3,000 hours
or 3,000 one-to-one sessions is
a minimum. And I know there
are a lot of you that are thinking,
"But I want to go
to Bali. I want to earn good money.
I want to have the car.
I want the freedom." But these hours,
although they may not pay the most amount
of money you've ever seen,
you will still earn from these hours in
weeks and months
to come, and I'll explain why.
In these sessions,
you get to learn people.
You get to learn their problems.
You get to learn why they're really with
you.
You get to understand why their squat
isn't working.
You get to understand that Bob
is a bit taller and needs to do a sumo
deadlift
instead of a traditional one.
You get to appreciate what people
are like, how long
they want to train for,
what their pain points and problems are.
Because in the consult, they go, "Oh,
I just want to be a bit fitter." But then
three months in,
you realize they're conspiring to get in
the best shape of their
life because they broke up with their ex.
Understanding these things
is imperative for how you communicate with
people
online in time to come.
Without understanding their problems by
spending weeks and
maybe even months with them,
you're going to really struggle to
resonate with
people on the internet.
I did over 5,000 hours of one-to-one,
which is why I was
able to put my finger on the pulse of what
people wanted to run a successful
business in the first place.
My business is not successful because I'm
a
businessman.
It's because I spent a lot of time working
with the exact people that
I still help now. Even if you
were to get paid £30, £40 an hour,
this information
that you learn from working with people in
person is
worth so much over time.
I can't even begin to explain.
But this doesn't mean you can't work on
critical things that are important to your
business whilst accruing these thousands
of hours, which brings me to number two,
to build an email list.
People buy from emails.
I call it the right time effect.
For instance,
say I'm swiping on social media and I see,
oh my God, I saw one of those
Ninja blender shakers yesterday.
So you just put all your fruit
and your protein in, whatever,
and then you can take
it out with you, put a bit of ice in it,
press the button.
It was like, I need that.
I need one of those in my life.
But I'm on my phone.
I don't buy stuff from my phone. Maybe
if it's got PayPal, but very rarely.
Now, let me tell you when I do buy things.
It's in the morning,
I'm going through my email list.
Amazon recommends Ninja.
Yep, cool.
Press the fingerprint on my MacBook.
Bought it. Comes in.
Next day, Amazon parcel turns up.
I can't even remember what came.
When I'm doing my emails,
I'm not checking my emails whilst I'm on
my phone.
Oh, yeah, just checking out YouTube,
whatever.
People check their emails at a point in
the day where it is important, it is
precious. They put headphones on.
They're in a cafe.
It is the effect
that you need to have on people.
Because if you try
and sell to people on social media
when everyone else is trying
to sell to them,
it's like chatting up a girl at the bar
when there's 10 dudes
all waiting to hit on her.
You'd be way better to just push in,
"Excuse me,
I'd really like to get your number." Then
you do the communications that you need
for the sale away from the bar that's busy
with other people in there, and
you do it when she's at work on Monday
when she's bored at her desk looking to
kill
time. Email marketing may seem old school,
but it's a bit like YouTube.
It's one of those constant variables
that over time has just remained amazing
and
excellent. And the reason
that people don't tell you so much about
emails is they
don't want you signing up people to your
email list because we want them on ours.
Not to mention,
if you talk about selling things on your
social media in
that content that you put out,
the video will die because people don't
like being
sold to. The reason
that people go to social media,
the same reason you go to
social media is you kind of want to be
entertained.
You want your mundane day to look
that little bit better,
so you look to something
online. And there is funny content.
And if you're like me,
you might just watch videos of people fall
over all day.
I am one of FailArmy's best
viewers. But people actually
are kind of looking for a hybrid of
entertainment and
education,
which is why I hope you're watching this
video here.
If I was just trying to sell you into my
online business mentorship course or
personal training, you'd be like,
"I'm off. I want information.
I want education." So it's best
that any selling or any mentions of your
products
are done offline. Again,
you don't chat to a girl at the bar
and go,
"What's your favorite thing in bed?" Well,
you might do.
That's a way better discussion to have
after you've had three dates with them and
you're laying at home in bed watching
Netflix and your parents have just gone
out
for a few hours. Where were we?
So it's important
that you can take people to an
email list and you can communicate with
them.
And better yet, even if they say, "Oh,
James, I've only got 12 people on my email
list." Well, you should email
that list still every day if you want to.
I do think daily emails
are the best way to do it.
I think you get about 40% more sales
versus emailing once a week.
But wouldn't it be nice
that you get better at email marketing as
your list grows?
Because if I gave you 10,000 people to
start emailing now, that list would riddle
down quite quick because you're shit at
email marketing.
Over the next 10 to 15 seconds,
you're going to think I'm a massive prick,
but I'm
a "Sunday Times" number one bestselling
author three times. That's number one.
Not like top 10. Some people are like,
"Oh, I'm a 'Sunday Times' best-selling
author." You're like, "Yeah, top 10,
sure." But that number one spot
three times was because of email
marketing.
It's because my email list
is better than my ability as an author.
There were way better authors in the third
and fourth slot.
They just didn't have a big email
marketing list.
100,000 people going through the James
Smith Academy, eight-figure business,
email
marketing. It's not even that I'm
that good at a personal trainer.
It's that I've got the big email list.
What else? Sold-out tours, events.
I wish it was me, but it
was my email list.
So number two, email marketing.
Now we look to number three, which is the
piece of technology that's been around for
quite a while, but it gives us the
opportunity that our parents,
our grandparents,
actually no one else in the history
of the universe has ever had before.
And if we utilize this thing right,
we can tap into potentially millions of
people, pay off our parents' mortgage,
have the dream car we want in our 30s,
and lay down on planes. And that thing,
number three, is social media.
Social media being stage three actually
helps you with stage two.
And the only reason really you should be
using social media is to get their
information.
That can sound quite reductive
and make you seem like you're some kind
of robot, but let me explain. Dating
and a sales funnel, they're very similar.
You might have heard me talk about this
before.
When we go out, if you wanted to have sex,
you actually don't just go out and say,
"I want sex." You put yourself in a
position.
There are loads of people
that would be right to have sex,
like a nightclub, which
is what social media is.
And then you're in that nightclub.
See people on the dance floor. "No,
not right for me, not right for me.
This person's right for me." Remember,
you're not trying to get everyone to sleep
with you in the club.
You're actually going to go out,
find the type of woman that
you want, or man. And when you find
that person You just talk, you get them
to know you, like you,
and trust you to the point you get their
information.
A lot of the time, if you're classy,
as I was, you would say,
"Lovely to meet you,"
kiss on the cheek, next day,
drop them a little message.
"Lovely to meet you last night.
If possible,
do you want to meet for a drink?" You
would have to get maybe 10 numbers to get
seven dates.
My case, obviously 10 dates. To get that,
three of them would be
right. One of them,
you might have a little relo
that goes for a few months till
they get a bit clingy,
then say they want you to go to a wedding
as a guest, and
you ghost them and never talk to them
again.
Sales funnel operates in a very much
similar way.
The main reason we're on social media
or on the dance floor
is we just want their
information so we can take them away from
there and communicate with them in a
means where they can get to know us,
like us, and trust us.
We send them emails,
but not about fitness.
We talk about the last argument you had
with your wife.
Tell them about the dog that's barking
next door and that won't shut up.
You even get a big bill for something,
make it an email.
Something you watched on Netflix,
Anything that happens in your life.
Tell them why you've got 11 chickens.
Why have you got 11 chickens? That
is where the majority of sales can be
made.
If you can see your social media funnel as
dating, you don't need to be
intimidated by the dance floor,
it's just the place to get numbers.
You might get some, you might not.
Social media is just a place to get
contact
information. You might get some,
you might not.
How do you improve both processes?
Well,
you get better at chatting up people,
and you get better at social media and
content creation. One thing that I
was pretty late to,
but we've started teaching
this in some of my mentorships,
is about using chatbots.
I was always against chatbots,
but I found out recently
that some of them have been
bought by Meta.
So you can actually get people to DM you,
and they can set up
automations to get them to join your list.
So Etienne, can you get your phone out,
please?
Okay, I want you to go to my Instagram
and show the camera my Instagram.
Go to any one of my posts, Etienne.
You're on a post?
Now comment, "Daddy."
Now, go to the DMs. Did you get a message?
And what does that message say?
"Well, Rob,
social media is a crazy place to try to
understand fat loss, training, and
nutrition." And where does that send them,
Etienne? To the email list.
You like that, don't you?
So I bet you thought people
were going manually through
the back end and, "Best reply to
that person that DM'd me." No, there
are bots in
place that you could use.
And this means that
when you do a piece of content
similar to this video,
you can just give people the prompts
necessary at the end to
say, "Hey." And the word daddy,
I used it because it's volatile.
It's sexual innuendos. It's a word
that gets people to laugh.
There are people going, "Daddy?
That's horrendous.
That's what girls with daddy problems
would call their dad or lover."
And by doing
so,
we are reducing the barrier for someone to
contact us.
Then instead of just saying, "Hey,
click the link in my bio,"
which I did for years
and made millions doing, this way
is just an easier way to do so.
In my last reel,
I got 1,000 email addresses in 24 hours by
doing this.
And if you want to know the exact way to
set that up, again, it's something I teach
in the mentorship.
But the main reason we're using content
and social media is to
build an audience of people that know you,
like you, and trust you.
And if you do 3,000 sessions of
face-to-face PT, you'll have 500 to
1,000, if not more,
content ideas from that alone.
You just got paid an hourly rate to do
market research with the demographic that
are going to pay you over the next few
years. It's beautiful.
Here's a case study.
I was training a client in the gym.
She asked me about her menstrual cycle
and how
it was impacted by training.
I told her I didn't know.
I went away and listened to a podcast,
did a video on it the next day.
This was before I even had a big
following.
14 million views on Facebook from a video.
That gave me 14,000 new people following
me within a week because I was listening
to my client. This
is where the beauty of working with people
and understanding
their problems and listening, remember,
you've got two ears and one mouth for a
reason,
can pay the big bucks down the line.
Which brings me onto number four,
something you can do.
Some of my friends do it.
I don't really think you should be doing
it. No, I've never done it.
Number four, never do brand deals.
Because it's the sign of running a shitty
business.
Because if your business is good,
you don't need to get paid a few percent
from
MyProtein. "Hey, guys,
use my MyProtein code." It's beggy.
And if I think that you're going to scrape
together a few posts to promote Gymshark
to get a few quid, I'm like,
"This guy can't be that good," or,
"This woman can't
be that good a business."
If she's dropping her pants to get
Gymshark to give her a
few pennies of commission,
the business can't be cranking.
The goal isn't to get sponsored by
MyProtein.
The goal is to earn enough that
when MyProtein come knocking,
you go like this,
"Oh, yeah. Nice one,
MyProtein." You don't want a brand to tell
you what to do.
Bit like the time
that I used to wear Vans
and skateboard everywhere, but they said
I couldn't use the C-word in content
anymore if they were to do an endorsement
with
me, so I told them where to go.
I think the brand deals can cheapen your
offering,
and if you're going to do it for anything
other than money, it's just going to
damage your reputation.
If you have a business,
you want to make more money, help
more people, change more lives,
get more clients, grow your list,
grow your socials.
Don't sell your soul to protein companies.
Which brings me onto step number five,
which is what most coaches probably
struggle
to think of. And if they can be unique
and original with this idea, they can get
ahead of all of their competitors.
And number five is to create free digital
assets.
There is something
that people need from you.
And remember,
people aren't just going to give you their
information for no reason.
If you're a specialist in glute training,
maybe make a glute guide.
If you're a meditation breathwork,
make a guide.
If you're a fat loss coach,
make a calorie calculator.
Then exchange these for people's email
addresses.
Perhaps even run paid ads on this,
or again, use a chatbot.
For my course, the business mentorship,
we run paid ads on an email
sign-up.
I pay about 40p per email address,
which is very good because quite a
large percentage of people
that end up getting the emails end up
joining the
program. But anyway,
if you can think of a good asset you can
give people, you will
get a lot of email addresses.
But let me make this clear.
Stop sending eBooks. Right? "Oh,
I've written an
eBook. It's 200 pages." Stop. I am,
as you remember before,
when I got my cock out
and measured it, three times best seller.
I struggle to sell books, right?
I spend a year writing something.
I work with a world-renowned publisher,
and
still I say, "Hey, buy my book."
And people say no.
So when you scratched up an eBook in your
spare time, sat at the local café having
a cup of Costa Coffee, it's no wonder
that people aren't giving you email
addresses
from it. People don't want books.
They've got enough books.
If you've written an eBook,
how many chapters? It's got 36. Cool.
That's 36 different digital assets to give
away.
Don't do it all in one,
because the biggest issue you can make
with this is giving
people too much.
I saw Andrew Schultz stand up a few months
ago.
Amazing, perfect. When he left,
my girlfriend was crying. It
was beautiful.
Went to see Theo Von, 35 minutes too long.
And I like Theo Von.
My favorite type of weed is cocaine.
I like Theo Von.
But what I should never have felt like
is sat in my chair
going,
"I wish this finished 20 minutes ago."
And if people have that with your
digital asset that you're giving them in
return for their email address,
they're going to think,
"I'm not going to buy this program because
it's probably
going to be too long." It's another reason
I make these videos as succinct and
short as possible,
because the videos in my program
are short and succinct as
possible.
You don't want to sit for an hour to learn
about a topic when I could in
12 minutes give you eight different topics
to then research for life.
So with your assets, make them short,
make them sweet.
When they finish it,
they give you their email address,
they go, "Bloody hell.
I wish..." There was a little bit more.
I can't wait to get stuck into this
person's program because that
was beautiful.
You are better off leaving someone wanting
more than giving them too much.
Which brings me on to number six,
the real way that you're going to get
yourself to
go to a six-figure business,
because although it
is possible doing it face-to-face,
it's very expensive
and depending on the geographic location
of where you are, they
just may not be the people
that can afford that.
But good news is if you do what you can do
in number six, you can tap into people
that aren't restricted by the amount of
financial offerings they have because you
are going to, number six,
create an online offering.
Coaching as an example.
Because when you work online,
you think how many people within these
four walls
could I get in to pay me a lot of money?
Probably a few. Do you know where I am?
Joking. But within 15-minute drive,
there's only going to be a certain amount
of
people that could afford my services.
But when I go online,
suddenly we've got billions,
literally nearly 10 billion
people.
So when you create an online offering,
which is going to be your services,
because again, not to get sidetracked,
okay, but we can create products and
services.
So a service would be you coaching
someone, but a product could be
something they could buy. Remember,
golden rule, you can discount a product,
you
never discount a service.
That's another video altogether.
But your first thing you're going to do
over time is reduce your in-person session
hours. I dialed them back from 6:00 a.m.
till 2:00 p.m.
It meant that my business in the short
term made less money,
but then I could work
on more of an online strategy
and save energy for that and trust me,
it worked out
well. I drive a nice car. [engine revving]
Oh my.
But if you can reduce your in-person
sessions, maybe 3,000 hours in,
you can start
to then work online in the afternoon.
It's quite nice leaving the gym.
It's even better when someone says to you,
"Hi, John.
I'm looking for a personal trainer.
I finish work at 5:30 so if we could
start at 6:00 p.m." And you go, "Mate,
I don't do evening sessions." This
was me a
few years ago. Someone's like,
"What do you mean you don't do evening
sessions?
They're your bread and butter." I said,
"Mate, I get in here at 6:00 a.m.
I'm not being seen dead in this gym after
3:00 p.m." Your dentist wouldn't work 15
hours, there's no reason you should.
So that's beautiful.
When you shorten your day,
you cram all your clients into the first
bit, and you
leave that gym at 2:00 p.m.
knowing you're not coming back for like
another 18
hours.
You build an online community of your
paying members.
Put them in a group together,
let them chat,
put them in a Facebook group, whatever
it is. Now,
to be a six-figure online coach,
which sounds cringey.
Americans, right?
"I'm an entrepreneur." "Go get it, man.
Land of the free." In England,
you don't say that.
You tell someone in England you're an
entrepreneur, they'll slap you, because we
don't like to hear about people making
money because they think it's like a
zero-sum game where if you're rich,
we must be poor to accommodate.
It's why they hate billionaires.
Billionaires get more hate than
millionaires, even
though they probably employ more people.
Anyway, stop getting distracted.
If you want to be a six-figure coach,
that's 8,333 pounds per calendar month.
So if you had 55 people paying you 37
pound 87 a week, you're on
100K. Again, 55 people sounds too many.
You could have half
that amount of people paying you 70 pound.
You know what I mean? Now again,
you're probably thinking why would someone
charge
37 pound 80 a week?
Surely we want to get the money off them
up front.
Surely we want to get them paying high
ticket six months up front.
Which brings me onto number seven,
the one biggest battle we can play in
psychology
that not many people tap into, and
if they get this right,
they could make more
money, and that is number seven, pricing.
I prefer weekly versus monthly.
I think it reduces the barrier to entry.
The only reason you'd be truly concerned
with doing weekly versus monthly is that
someone would join for a week or two
and then they would leave.
Which is fair enough, but even
if they pay for six months up front,
most of
you legally are obliged to give them a
refund within the first 14 days as part of
their consumer rights.
So why not remove
that massive barrier to entry, let them
pay weekly, don't get the money up front,
get them in your system, and instead of
worrying about them leaving within the
first two to four weeks,
serve them well and
be a great flipping coach so
that they won't leave.
If your offering and service is good,
it shouldn't matter how they pay you.
And the fact you can put your hand up
and say, "Pay me weekly.
My course is amazing, my coaching amazing.
You get your program on time."
That gives them confidence, which
is what they want.
They just don't want to waste their time.
They've wasted their time before.
Rather than being like,
"I need 1,200 pounds up front for 6 months
of coaching."
"Nah. Just give us 40 pound a week
and I take care of everything.
Anything up front, don't worry about it.
I've got great coaching." "Oh,
other places ask them to pay up front."
They
probably do because they're poo,
all right? I prefer weekly.
And also people are comparing PT to the
weekly price, and they'll pay them before.
No one goes, "Oh, how much is
that PT an hour?" "It's 200 pounds a
month." They
say, "Yeah, it's 40,
50 pound an hour." And
if you come in at a weekly rate,
they're going to compare
that to the existing personal trainer.
So if you're charging 40 pounds a week
and they're currently paying 80 pound for
an
hour of PT, you now get to say,
"My online coaching
is all of your programs.
It works out better value than the one
you're doing.
You're only getting an hour with
that guy or woman, and
that one hour isn't enough
because you've got to wait another six
days and 23 hours to ask them another
question.
But if you're in my online program,
you haven't got to worry about that."
Again, if you want to charge monthly,
charge monthly. I'm not your dad.
Personally,
I love to use WhatsApp for my
communications.
A lot of people think they need to have a
fancy app. They don't.
Look at this, four-finger swipe.
Don't look too carefully.
That's private information.
I just chat to my clients
there because do you know why?
I don't want the relationship with my
client to feel
like, "Oh,
you are paying me for professional
services.
We will only communicate via emails like
you would with a lawyer when you buy a
house." No.
And I'm not jumping on weekly check-ins
with you.
I hate phone calls. But guess what, Steve?
If you need me, drop me a voice note.
"Hi, James. Went to the gym today.
The squat rack was full
and there was a bit of a queue so I
was wondering what could be possible
that I
could potentially do instead of that?"
Don't worry, Steve.
Let me send you a voice note back. "Hey,
Steve. Lovely to hear from you.
Glad you got in touch.
Do love to hear from my clients.
Well,
next time if you're looking for something,
maybe we do a rift elevated split
squat on a bench,
or you could even use a plyometric box in
the functional room
that I remember seeing
when you sent me a video on WhatsApp of
your gym
setup when we started." That's easier for
them.
Again,
it reduces barriers to communication
because if they're going to communicate
with their loved ones, their friends,
and their family through WhatsApp,
why don't
you add yourself to that list?
You don't need a fancy app. It helps.
I have a coach, he's in America,
he's very smart and pretty expensive,
and he sends
me all of my programs on an Excel
spreadsheet.
Which moves us on to number eight.
The one thing that I know you probably
don't want to focus on too much, but
if you just would
and just put the hours in,
trust me,
it can create a similar weapon to what I'm
using today, and that number
eight is, yes, content. I know
that it's better off having the right
message
on the wrong camera than it
is the wrong message on the right camera.
But having a good quality microphone,
having a good camera, and even having the
ability to talk to a camera,
you probably think, "Oh,
this guy's a natural." Stop
it. I've been doing this 10 years.
10 years.
If you did anything for 10 years,
you'd be good at it. All right?
When I started, I was awkward. "Hi,
my name is James.
I'm a personal trainer."
But I've been doing this a long time,
and the only way to
get better is through doing it more.
Imagine doing Olympic lifting.
You try your first snatch,
it looks terrible. How
are you going to get better?
Read a book on doing snatches.
Do more snatches.
Course correct as you go along.
Oh, that was bad. Don't do it again. Oh,
that felt good. Do more of it.
People seem to think
that they can get good at every element of
their business
within 30 days or a month. Trust me,
it doesn't.
It will take me 10 years to become a black
belt.
Right now,
I've been training jujitsu pretty much
full time for six years.
Got my brown belt a few months ago,
and I just lost three out of three matches
at
the weekend. That's six years
and I'm still crap.
So you can't expect your content creation
to become amazing within a year.
But within three years,
maybe at the 10-year mark,
I'll get my black belt and it
will all be worth it.
Then my opportunities to monetize,
to make content,
to be an authority within
that space become real.
If I'm going to spend 10 years of
full-time training to accomplish a belt,
you can
put in one year of solid content
and all the things I've done without
expecting online clients to flourish
and to fly first class to Dubai.
It took me four years of doing the exact
thing I'm talking to you about before I
got my first online client.
It took me four years to get 10,000
followers.
It took me four more years to hit a
million.
If you can be patient and appreciate
and respect the things that I've told you
about,
you can really do well as a personal
trainer.
We spoke a lot about emails
and the power of email marketing,
and I'm going to show
you in real practice just how well this
works by putting a link in the description
where over the next month,
every single day,
I'm going to email you a really
important nugget of wisdom for your
business which is going to revolutionize
your
life.
But the only way you can get more
information than this initial video for
free is give me your best email address.
Click the link in the description.
Thank you very much for watching.
And you're probably thinking,
"What's in it for
me?" Good question. One,
the majority of personal trainers never
see their second
year. The reason that's shit is that
when people now go to the gym, all the
coaches are inexperienced
and they don't understand problems,
haven't worked with
enough people.
If I can help PTs run better businesses,
we have happier
coaches with more flourishing businesses
that are more experienced.
That means that people get helped better.
Better standard of coaches,
better standard of expertise equals a
better
environment for people that need help.
And secondly,
because I get paid really well.